<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Mooplog - Games</title><link href="https://mooped.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://mooped.github.io/feeds/games.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://mooped.github.io/</id><updated>2015-03-15T21:25:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>Foobot</title><link href="https://mooped.github.io/foobot.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-03-15T21:25:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-03-15T21:25:00+00:00</updated><author><name>moop</name></author><id>tag:mooped.github.io,2015-03-15:/foobot.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Foobot is a project I started around November 2014. It's still a work in
progress, but the time when I should have written it up is more than
due.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2015/03/15/foobot/foobot_complete/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Foobot" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-804" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/foobot_complete.jpg" style="width: 1024px; height: 576px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Foobot is robot table football game, with two teams of two tiny adorable
robots. The robots are controlled by classic Nintendo …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Foobot is a project I started around November 2014. It's still a work in
progress, but the time when I should have written it up is more than
due.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2015/03/15/foobot/foobot_complete/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Foobot" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-804" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/foobot_complete.jpg" style="width: 1024px; height: 576px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Foobot is robot table football game, with two teams of two tiny adorable
robots. The robots are controlled by classic Nintendo and Sega
controllers, hopefully it can can finally settle the age old console
wars. :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2015/03/15/foobot/foobot_robots/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Foobot Robots" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-801" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/foobot_robots.jpg" style="width: 1920px; height: 1080px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The intention eventually is to build some games around these robots.
Possibly with the ability for a computer to control some of the robots
via some image processing if I'm feeling really ambitious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The robots are built around an ATtiny2313 microcontroller, with an
SN754410 to control the motors and a cheap 1402 433mhz radio receiver
module. This is mounted on a simple laser cut perspex frame with two
wheels mounted directly onto the motors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2015/03/15/foobot/foobot_parts/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Foobot Parts" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-800" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/foobot_parts.jpg" style="width: 1920px; height: 1359px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The initial design was built on stripboard, but once I had it working I
ordered a professionally made PCB via &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dirtypcbs.com/"&gt;http://dirtypcbs.com/&lt;/a&gt;. This was
the first PCB I've had made and the quality turned out to be better than
expected for the price and the 3 week shipping was pretty bearable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the radio modules are very simple (and one way) I decided to avoid
the problem of collisions between multiple transmitters by attaching the
controllers for all players to a single radio transmitter. The
transmitter reads all of the controllers and then sends a packet
addressed to each robot in turn. Messages for the robots consist of a
robot ID, the message payload and a checksum. Robots ignore all messages
not addressed to them and any messages with invalid checksums. Dropped
packets or interference are dealt with by hoping the next message with
more up to date data will arrive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2015/03/15/foobot/transmitter_perpsective/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Transmitter Unit" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-803" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/transmitter_perpsective.jpg" style="width: 1920px; height: 1080px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The transmitter module is based around a tiny 8 pin ATtiny13
microcontroller. This has just enough pins to read data from all of the
controllers and to send a signal to the transmitter module. Some of the
lines are shared with the In-Circuit Programming interface for the
microcontroller - these were chosen to be the outputs so there was no
need to worry about other hardware interfering with programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to read 4 controllers with 4 pins the transmitter uses a pair
of controller interface boards. These have a socket for a NES controller
(which contains a shift register so the button states can be read out
serially) and a 74LS165 shift register which enables the Master System
controller to behave like a NES controller (it is just 6 buttons with a
shared common pin). The 75LS165's latch line is inverted so a transistor
was required to invert this in order for the same latch signal to
operate both devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2015/03/15/foobot/transmitter_parts/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Transmitter Parts" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-802" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/transmitter_parts.jpg" style="width: 1920px; height: 1157px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this setup the only extra pins required on the microcontroller are
shared latch and clock signals and a data line for each NES/Master
System controller pair. The serial output from the NES shift register is
passed into the serial input on the 74LS165 so sending a latch and 15
pulses reads 8 buttons (2 unused) from the Master System controller and
then 8 buttons from the NES controller. The Master System buttons are
mapped so they come out in the same order as the buttons with equivalent
functions on the NES controller (A, B, Select, Start, Up, Down, Left,
Right and 2, 1, N/A, N/A, Up, Down, Left, Right).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of the transmitter the circuit was initially tested on a
breadboard. This proved quite fragile due to the flying leads to the
various controllers so I ordered some more custom boards. The price
break on DirtyPCBs is at 5x5cm, so I designed a single board containing
the controller interface and a board to carry the microcontroller in a
single 5x5 square. I designed tabs into the board outline to allow the
two boards to be broken apart. When fully assembled the transmitter
contains two of the controller interface board and one of the
microcontroller board, so there will be some spares of the smaller
board. The cheapest quantity from DirtyPCB is a protopack of 9-12 boards
(I got 11 both times), but I only need one transmitter currently so that
works out just fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I struggled to motors that are both cheap and small without a
ridiculously high RPM. The motors I settled on in the end run at around
16000 RPM and 9 volts. Because of this I had to add some code to pulse
width modulate the enable pin on the motor controller. Turning requires
very little force so it runs with a very low duty cycle. When moving
forward initially the motors run at full power to get the robot moving,
after a short delay the duty cycle is lowered to avoid accelerating too
fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuning the PWM settings has proven fiddly, and testing with the
programmer attached is almost useless as the wires affect the motion of
the robot too much. Because of this I implemented an over the air update
of the PWM settings. This added some extra commands to update the PWM
duty cycles over the radio, and a command to write the to the
microcontroller's EEPROM to save them permanently once the behaviour
feels right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've uploaded the project to
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/mooped/foobot"&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;, including all of the
code, schematics, PCB layouts and chassis/case CAD files. Feel free to
use these, but please bear in mind that the project is still a work in
progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, here's a video of some Foobots in action (before the over the
air PWM tuning feature went in):&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="Foobot"></category><category term="Games"></category></entry><entry><title>Loot of the Forest</title><link href="https://mooped.github.io/loot-of-the-forest.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-12-15T23:18:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-12-15T23:18:00+00:00</updated><author><name>moop</name></author><id>tag:mooped.github.io,2013-12-15:/loot-of-the-forest.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just finished participating in the 28th Ludum Dare game jam. This time
around the theme was 'You Only Get One'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I chose to interpret this fairly literally as a game mechanic and came
up with Loot of the Forest. It's a game about bribing forest guardian
creatures as you …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just finished participating in the 28th Ludum Dare game jam. This time
around the theme was 'You Only Get One'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I chose to interpret this fairly literally as a game mechanic and came
up with Loot of the Forest. It's a game about bribing forest guardian
creatures as you make your way through their forest maze, but you only
have a single item per species of guardian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2013/12/15/loot-of-the-forest/level2/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Loot of the Forest" class="size-full wp-image-512" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/level2.png" style="width: 571px; height: 479px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expect puzzles and weird animal based puns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Play it
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ludumdare.com/compo/ludum-dare-28/?action=preview&amp;amp;uid=2573"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game was written in HTML5/Javascript, with graphics drawn in GIMP,
and sound effects generated by the awesome ` &amp;lt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.bfxr.net/"&gt;http://www.bfxr.net/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;gt;`__.
It was fueled by sleep deprivation and cold pizza.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="Games"></category><category term="Loot of the Forest"></category><category term="Ludum Dare"></category></entry></feed>