<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Mooplog - Hi-Fly, Maiden Flights, Things</title><link href="https://www.moop.org.uk/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.moop.org.uk/feeds/hi-fly-maiden-flights-things.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.moop.org.uk/</id><updated>2013-03-03T00:31:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>Glider Restoration Part 4 - Finishing touches</title><link href="https://www.moop.org.uk/glider-restoration-part-4-finishing-touches.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-03-03T00:31:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-03-03T00:31:00+00:00</updated><author><name>moop</name></author><id>tag:www.moop.org.uk,2013-03-03:/glider-restoration-part-4-finishing-touches.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The weather today was unexpectedly awesome so it would have been a crime
to not try and take the glider out for a flight. I had to quickly make a
few finishing touches before it was ready to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First off the connectors were soldered to the motor and ESC …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The weather today was unexpectedly awesome so it would have been a crime
to not try and take the glider out for a flight. I had to quickly make a
few finishing touches before it was ready to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First off the connectors were soldered to the motor and ESC and the
motor was mounted to the pylon. Ultimately, this needs further finishing
work, but I'd like to make sure the motor is suited to the job before
doing anything more permanent. The elastic band will keep the wires
clear of the prop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;quot;attachment_224&amp;quot; align=&amp;quot;alignnone&amp;quot; width=&amp;quot;1024&amp;quot;]&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/?attachment_id=224"&gt;&lt;img alt="Motor pod/pylon" class="size-full wp-image-224" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/2013-03-03-00.03.55.jpg" style="width: 1024px; height: 613px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Motor pod/pylon[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The clearance between the pod and the wing limits the prop to about 5
inches. I'm running a 5x5 prop with a 1650Kv (ie. 1650 RPM/volt) motor
from a 3 cell Lithium Polymer battery. Hopefully this will provide
enough thrust, if not I may have to try a 3000Kv motor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought some large 5&amp;quot; rubber bands to hold the wing and stabiliser on,
as the ones from the original kit had perished. To protect the trailing
edge of the wing from being crushed by the bands I installed a pair of
ply plates on the rear of the wings. I first cut away the covering from
a section of the wing and then epoxied on some 1/32&amp;quot; ply plates. These
were then recovered with a small rectangle of film to neaten them up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[gallery ids=&amp;quot;218,220,221&amp;quot;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this done the model is now in a state where it is ready to fly, and
can be stored fully assembled. This made storing it a bit easier since
it can hang on the wall above my desk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;quot;attachment_222&amp;quot; align=&amp;quot;alignnone&amp;quot; width=&amp;quot;1024&amp;quot;]&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/?attachment_id=222"&gt;&lt;img alt="New home" class="size-full wp-image-222" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/2013-03-02-22.06.37.jpg" style="width: 1024px; height: 613px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; New home[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I took it out to the field for a test flight. Fortunately a few
other members of the Derby Model Aero Club were also out making use of
the nice weather, so I was able to get a hand launch and a cameraman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The model flew nicely as a glider. Unfortunately I only had a small
battery charged which wasn't really capable of running the motor for an
extended period without taking some damage. I also had to add a second
heavier but incompatible battery for ballast to get the centre of
gravity correct. Next time I have opportunity to fly it I'll use a
larger battery so I can gain enough altitude for a proper test.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry></feed>