<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Mooplog - RC2014, Things</title><link href="https://mooped.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://mooped.github.io/feeds/rc2014-things.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://mooped.github.io/</id><updated>2016-10-30T23:13:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>Retrochallenge 2016/10 - Breadboard Fun</title><link href="https://mooped.github.io/retrochallenge-201610-breadboard-fun.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-10-30T23:13:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-10-30T23:13:00+00:00</updated><author><name>moop</name></author><id>tag:mooped.github.io,2016-10-30:/retrochallenge-201610-breadboard-fun.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Having finally found time to start breadboarding my SD card interface I
first made sure that the edge trigger circuit I had tested in ModelSim
would work when built with real components.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An issue I had encountered previously when breadboarding RC2014
peripherals was that if I wanted to disconnect the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Having finally found time to start breadboarding my SD card interface I
first made sure that the edge trigger circuit I had tested in ModelSim
would work when built with real components.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An issue I had encountered previously when breadboarding RC2014
peripherals was that if I wanted to disconnect the circuit from the
RC2014 I would lose track of which wire was which. To work around this
this time I took an unused RC2014 protoboard module and soldered on just
the usual 90 pin header and a socket header below it. The protoboard can
still be used later (minus one row of holes) and now provides something
that wires can be plugged into that can be removed from the RC2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2016/10/30/retrochallenge-201610-breadboard-fun/img_20161024_211944-jpg-sm/"&gt;&lt;img alt="RC2014 Protoboard" class="size-full wp-image-992" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/IMG_20161024_211944.jpg.sm_.jpg" style="width: 1024px; height: 766px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the edge trigger circuit built I tested it using my &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dangerousprototypes.com/blog/open-logic-sniffer/"&gt;Open Logic
Sniffer&lt;/a&gt;,
which has been an invaluable tool for many projects. I did however
notice that running on the RC2014's 8mhz clock brings the Open Logic
Sniffer quite close to its limits. The 200mhz maximum sample rate
provides resolution for only about 12 steps within each clock cycle, so
there is limited scope for playing with gate delays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2016/10/30/retrochallenge-201610-breadboard-fun/img_20161024_214406-jpg-sm/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Edge Detect" class="size-full wp-image-994" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/IMG_20161024_214406.jpg.sm_.jpg" style="width: 1024px; height: 766px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the edge detect circuit was proven to work I started building the
rest of the circuit and things quickly got complicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2016/10/30/retrochallenge-201610-breadboard-fun/img_20161030_161426-jpg-sm/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Blinkenlights" class="size-full wp-image-995" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/IMG_20161030_161426.jpg.sm_.jpg" style="width: 1024px; height: 766px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The image above shows the almost complete circuit, but with a loopback
between the input and output shift registers where the SD card would
normally fit, and some blinkenlights on the outputs from the input shift
register to indicate its state before it was connected to the data bus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent quite a long time debugging why the signal coming into the input
shift register was always off by one bit. Initially I blamed timing
issues in the glue logic and spent quite a while experimenting with
inserting delays to try and fix things. Eventually I realised that I was
clocking both the Shift Clock Pulse input of the 74HCT595 and the Store
Clock Pulse (which latches values from the shift register to the output
shift register) with the same clock signal. This resulted in the output
register always showing the last but one state of the shift register.
Switching the Store Clock Pulse input to an inverted copy of the clock
signal fixed this and I was able to send any byte from the output shift
register to the input shift register with the circuit operating in
autoshift mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously when breadboarding I had been building the circuit in KiCAD,
planning out the breadboard layout as PCB, then building the circuit
based on that design. Any changes made on the breadboard had to be
updated in KiCAD or things got very confusing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately this mechanism got onerous once I started making changes
on the breadboard. Following traces on the screen is no easier than
following them in the real world and long jumper wires were hard to
route in KiCAD without using many extra layers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the most recent attempt I decided to try a more old school approach
and build a netlist representing the breadboard contents on paper. I
made and printed some templates in Google Sheets, annotated the existing
breadboarded design onto the sheet, then kept it up to date as things
changed. This turned out to be a lot more convenient than keeping track
of the design in KiCAD as it was easy to search for a signal by name and
the paper was easier to reach on my desk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2016/10/30/retrochallenge-201610-breadboard-fun/img_20161030_221905-jpg-sm/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Paper Netlist" class="size-full wp-image-997" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/IMG_20161030_221905.jpg.sm_.jpg" style="width: 1024px; height: 766px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry></feed>