<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Mooplog - ShapeOko, Things</title><link href="https://mooped.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://mooped.github.io/feeds/shapeoko-things.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://mooped.github.io/</id><updated>2014-09-13T22:53:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>eShapeOko Part 3 - Tidying up</title><link href="https://mooped.github.io/eshapeoko-part-3-tidying-up.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-09-13T22:53:00+01:00</published><updated>2014-09-13T22:53:00+01:00</updated><author><name>moop</name></author><id>tag:mooped.github.io,2014-09-13:/eshapeoko-part-3-tidying-up.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Having had the ShapeOko for over a year now I've used it for quite a few
projects, but nowhere near as many as I intended. Part of the reason for
this is that the controller for the machine was still rather jury rigged
so setting it up was a hassle …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Having had the ShapeOko for over a year now I've used it for quite a few
projects, but nowhere near as many as I intended. Part of the reason for
this is that the controller for the machine was still rather jury rigged
so setting it up was a hassle. To solve this problem I've been working
on integrating together a permanent version of the controller.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2014/09/13/eshapeoko-part-3-tidying-up/20140913_201752/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Finished Product" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-752" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/20140913_201752.jpg" style="width: 935px; height: 526px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started by designing a pair of custom PCBs with a bus to connect them
together while allowing for expansion. The first board is essentially an
Arduino with custom pin out. The second board mounts the stepper
controllers. At some point I may add a breakout board for limit switches
and a board to interface with a pendant for manually controlling the
machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2014/09/13/eshapeoko-part-3-tidying-up/20140715_202957/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Arduino and Stepper Boards" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-737" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/20140715_202957.jpg" style="width: 935px; height: 526px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having built the boards, they all work fine, but there are things I'd do
differently if I made another. First off I'd probably stick with a
standard Arduino pinout, both for reusability and because the 24 pin DIL
socket I used turned out to be expensive. Additionally, the layout for
the (single sided) boards would have been much simpler without the DIL
socket to consider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="arduino-board-underside-with-horrible-routing-for-the-dil-connector"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2014/09/13/eshapeoko-part-3-tidying-up/20140608_194934/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Arduino board underside with horrible routing for the DIL connector" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-741" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/20140608_194934.jpg" style="width: 935px; height: 526px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the boards made I decided on using an FTDI module I had lying
around for USB to serial conversion, replacing the Minimus that I was
using previously. I designed a very simple breakout for this module to
expose the Power, Reset, Ground and Serial Tx/Rx signals in a way that
matches the Arduino's FTDI header. The main benefit of the breakout
board, however, was that I could give it appropriate dimensions for
mounting in a case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all of the boards made and (a few months later, once a burst of
motivation turned up) assembled, I needed to build a case to keep the
parts together. I decided to laser cut the case from perspex in order to
get it made quickly—and because I thought a clear perspex case would
look cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to my earlier experiences with fried Stepper Controllers I decided
to use locking connectors to prevent accidental disconnection while the
machine was powered up. After some searching I found that 4 pin gx16
aviation connectors seemed to do what I want. I ended up ordering some
from China through Amazon as it was the cheapest source, though thanks
to the seller incorrectly filling in the customs form I paid more than
expected for them. Regardless, they work nicely and look good. I also
used one of these connectors for power, with two pins acting as 12v and
ground and spare pins for signalling. Should I choose to power the
machine from a PC power supply at a later date, one of these lines will
be used for the PSU's power on line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2014/09/13/eshapeoko-part-3-tidying-up/20140913_201732/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Locking Connectors" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-755" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/20140913_201732.jpg" style="width: 935px; height: 526px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the connectors and some switches chosen and measured, I began work
on designing the case. I settled on a fairly simple tabbed box design.
The box is split into two sections to match the two widths of board:
narrow USB to serial breakout and wide Arduino and Stepper Controller
boards. The sides of the box have slots into which various mounting
plates can be bolted. The boards locate into slots in the mounting
plates, allowing for quite flexible arrangement of the boards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2014/09/13/eshapeoko-part-3-tidying-up/20140619_204746/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Case Parts" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-738" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/20140619_204746.jpg" style="width: 935px; height: 526px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2014/09/13/eshapeoko-part-3-tidying-up/20140619_215111/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Runners for board mounting" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-735" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/20140619_215111.jpg" style="width: 935px; height: 526px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the case parts cut, I found it fairly fiddly to assemble, but once
together it was quite sturdy. Some of the wires to the connectors had to
be soldered with parts of the case in place. This makes maintenance
slightly trickier, but will reduce the chance of intermittent
connections to the steppers which could exist if I'd used a second set
of connectors on the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2014/09/13/eshapeoko-part-3-tidying-up/20140715_224126/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Assembling the controller inside the case" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-742" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/20140715_224126.jpg" style="width: 935px; height: 526px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The layout of the connectors and switches was mostly determined by the
shape of the case and the space taken up by the boards. I ended up with
the stepper connectors on the top of the case in the same section as the
USB to serial adapter. The connectors are quite deep, so they required a
lot of space behind their mounting plate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2014/09/13/eshapeoko-part-3-tidying-up/20140913_201703/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Stepper connectors" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-754" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/20140913_201703.jpg" style="width: 935px; height: 526px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On one end of the case there is a cutout for the USB to serial board and
a reset switch for the Arduino in the form of a big red button. It's not
exactly an emergency stop button but should have a similar effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2014/09/13/eshapeoko-part-3-tidying-up/20140913_201740/"&gt;&lt;img alt="USB connector and reset switch" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-756" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/20140913_201740.jpg" style="width: 935px; height: 526px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other end is an extra gx16 connector for power and a switch that
will act as a power switch if a PC PSU is used. The switch is designed
to connect or disconnect the ATX PS_ON line instead of being directly
in line with the 12 volt input, which would require a sturdier switch.
There is space for mounting a much smaller alternative switch, but I
went with a large toggle in the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each end of the case has a grille and mounting holes for a 45mm fan
should extra cooling be required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2014/09/13/eshapeoko-part-3-tidying-up/20140913_201732/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Power switch and connector" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-755" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/20140913_201732.jpg" style="width: 935px; height: 526px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to keep the cables for the steppers tidy, I slipped on two
pieces of heat shrink over the paracord sheaths I added. These keep the
ends of the paracord neat at each end of the cable and provide a bit
more bulk so the strain relief in the connectors has something to grip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2014/09/13/eshapeoko-part-3-tidying-up/20140913_201752/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Finished Product" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-752" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/20140913_201752.jpg" style="width: 935px; height: 526px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>eShapeOko Part 2 - Mechanicals</title><link href="https://mooped.github.io/eshapeoko-part-2-mechanicals.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-10-22T21:01:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-10-22T21:01:00+01:00</updated><author><name>moop</name></author><id>tag:mooped.github.io,2013-10-22:/eshapeoko-part-2-mechanicals.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Building the mechanical parts of the eShapeOko was fairly
straightforward, but there are some problems and modifications I made
that are worth writing about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2013/08/27/eshapeoko-part-1/2013-04-24-17-30-15/"&gt;&lt;img alt="eShapeOko parts" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-398" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-04-24-17.30.15.jpg" style="width: 1024px; height: 613px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first task of the assembly was to tap the MakerSlide sections to add
a screw thread. This was my first try at tapping anything, but …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Building the mechanical parts of the eShapeOko was fairly
straightforward, but there are some problems and modifications I made
that are worth writing about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2013/08/27/eshapeoko-part-1/2013-04-24-17-30-15/"&gt;&lt;img alt="eShapeOko parts" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-398" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-04-24-17.30.15.jpg" style="width: 1024px; height: 613px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first task of the assembly was to tap the MakerSlide sections to add
a screw thread. This was my first try at tapping anything, but it was
less trouble than expected, except for a few trips into town to get a
tap and die set and some tapping lubricant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the MakerSlide was tapped, everything else pretty much just bolted
together, though it's worth taking the time to think about alignment and
get the spacers right early on. Sorting it out later may require taking
most of the machine apart again just to gain access. Once built, minor
adjustments to the alignment of the rails are less of a problem. The
process is to loosen the rails to be aligned, slide the axis that runs
on those rails to one extreme, tighten the bolts at that end, then
repeat for the other end of the axis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2013/08/27/eshapeoko-part-1/2013-04-25-22-12-30/"&gt;&lt;img alt="eShapeOko assembled" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-427" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-04-25-22.12.30.jpg" style="width: 1024px; height: 613px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing to note is that it's worth buying and installing limit
switches early, even if you won't wire them up immediately. There's not
a lot of space behind their mounting points, so it can be difficult or
impossible to get bolts in or to screw on a nut from behind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2013/10/22/eshapeoko-part-2-mechanicals/2013-10-22-20-58-20/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Limit Switch" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-469" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/2013-10-22-20.58.20.jpg" style="width: 1024px; height: 613px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When buying the kit I went for the dual X axis and dual Y stepper
options; I'd definitely recommend these. The dual X axis adds a second
section of MakerSlide to the stepper which provides extra rigidity and
prevents the Z axis from twisting about the X axis. The dual Y stepper
upgrade provides the necessary parts for mounting a second stepper motor
to drive the Y axis. I initially bought this but didn't add the second
stepper. I quickly noticed that the undriven side of the Y axis was
lagging behind quite dramatically. Adding the second stepper fixed this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With 4 stepper motors to drive there were initially a lot of wires
floating around and waiting to get snagged in a nearby moving part. To
help with this I ordered some 15ft of paracord from eBay for a few quid.
By removing the inner of the paracord and melting the ends of the outer
layer to prevent fraying, you can make a nice sheath to reduce the
number of cables and make them more manageable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[gallery ids=&amp;quot;426,458&amp;quot;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Threading the wires through the paracord was fiddly. The best method I
found was to use pieces of the inner to pull the wires through. First
thread one piece of the inner back through the outer, tie one end around
the first wire, then tie a second piece of inner to the wire in the same
place. Fold the wire back on itself to prevent the knots from slipping
off, and pull it through. This gives you one wire and one piece of inner
threaded through the outer. Untie the inner from the wire and tie the
other end to a new wire, then tie another piece of inner to the wire and
repeat the process. Do this for all the wires, being careful to not let
them slip out and to not lose the end inside the outer. You will
probably find that the outer will stretch and shrink in diameter, which
can fixed by holding the loose end of the wire and pulling the end of
the outer away from it, then manipulating the outer to transfer and
balance out the tension. This process is also handy for getting the
outer to sit neatly against the stepper motor at the end of the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[gallery ids=&amp;quot;435,441,445,451,450,452&amp;quot;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This process requires a lot of patience but produced nice results.
Curiously I found that although the second and third wires were quite
hard to pull through the fourth tended to be easier. This was probably
down to the reduced friction of dragging the wire against more wires and
less paracord outer, but it's a good reason not to give up if the third
wire seems hard to get through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2013/10/22/eshapeoko-part-2-mechanicals/2013-10-22-21-38-39/"&gt;&lt;img alt="MDF base and spoil board" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-471" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/2013-10-22-21.38.39.jpg" style="width: 1024px; height: 613px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially I had the machine mounted on some old laminate floor boards,
which weren't very stiff. This gave bad results for milling wood and
terrible results for milling PCBs. Moving to a sturdy chunk of 3/8&amp;quot; MDF
resolved this nicely. I have a sacrificial piece of thinner MDF on top
of this as a spoil board to preserve the base itself and to provide more
mounting options for materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2013/08/27/eshapeoko-part-1/2013-04-24-20-43-30/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Z axis leadscrew" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-416" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-04-24-20.43.30.jpg" style="width: 1024px; height: 613px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only real problem I've had with the machine so far is with the Z
axis. Unlike the other two axes the motion is transferred to the axis
via a leadscrew. The leadscrew passes through a flanged bearing
sandwiched between two aluminium plates. The motor is coupled to the
leadscrew with a RepRap style (I believe) flexible coupler.
Unfortunately the set screw that tightens the coupler to the threaded
rod can easily push the rod off centre, causing the shaft to wobble
unless some packing or tape is wrapped around the threaded rod.
Additionally, the rod is held in place vertically by a nut on either
side of the bearing. Depending on the precision with which the nuts were
made this also can result in the axis wobbling if the nuts are tightened
and the axis floating vertically if the nuts come lose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[gallery ids=&amp;quot;472,473&amp;quot;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The combination of two sources of wobble in the axis and nuts that can
come loose easily makes setting up the Z axis very fiddly and quite time
consuming. This is currently the main obstacle I've found that is making
PCB milling difficult. I've been able to tune out the wobble relatively
effectively, though I worry that it may have damaged the plastic runners
for the Z axis. I still need to fix the issue with the nuts coming
loose. The options for this that I've come up with so far involve either
threadlock or buying a second pair of nuts (it's an Acme thread so
common or garden nuts won't do it) but I've yet to commit to or try one
of these options.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>eShapeOko Part 1</title><link href="https://mooped.github.io/eshapeoko-part-1.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-08-27T18:28:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-08-27T18:28:00+01:00</updated><author><name>moop</name></author><id>tag:mooped.github.io,2013-08-27:/eshapeoko-part-1.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was partway through writing a draft for a post about PCB milling when
I realised I hadn't yet written anything about the machine I've been
using, so I think it's about time for a post about the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.makerslideeurope.com/eshapeoko-kits.html"&gt;eShapeOko&lt;/a&gt; CNC
machine I built.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ordered the mechanical kit only, so …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was partway through writing a draft for a post about PCB milling when
I realised I hadn't yet written anything about the machine I've been
using, so I think it's about time for a post about the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.makerslideeurope.com/eshapeoko-kits.html"&gt;eShapeOko&lt;/a&gt; CNC
machine I built.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ordered the mechanical kit only, so no motors or electronics were
included. To kill time while the much awaited parcel made its way to me,
I ordered a pair of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://schmalzhaus.com/EasyDriver/"&gt;EasyDriver&lt;/a&gt;
stepper controllers and some stepper motors to experiment with. The
EasyDriver boards aren't particularly cheap but very easy to use, just
supply power, ground, connections to the motor and signals for Step and
Direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I soldered some pin headers onto the boards to break out all of the pins
I needed. With them plugged into a breadboard I could easily experiment
with driving them via a Minimus USB microcontroller board. Thanks to the
simplicity of the stepper controllers I had it driving the motors nicely
within an hour, though unfortunately I shortly after discovered several
ways to fry the Allegro A3967 chip that the EasyDriver is based on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;quot;attachment_380&amp;quot; align=&amp;quot;alignnone&amp;quot;
width=&amp;quot;1024&amp;quot;]&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2013/08/27/eshapeoko-part-1/2013-03-01-06-31-13/"&gt;&lt;img alt="EasyDriver stepper boards" class="size-full wp-image-380" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-03-01-06.31.13.jpg" style="width: 1024px; height: 613px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; EasyDriver stepper
boards[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first mistake was forgetting to power off the boards while
unplugging a motor. The controller keeps the coils in the stepper motor
energised continuously in order to hold the motor steady. Suddenly
removing the load tends to fry the controller. When I make a permanent
controller board for the machine, I plan to use locking connectors to
avoid absent mindedly unplugging the motors in this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second mistake was playing around with circuit on the breadboard
while it was powered up. I accidentally connected the Step input to my
12v supply instead of the regulated 5v output that the EasyDriver
provides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either way, I now had two unusable EasyDriver boards. Fortunately the
A3967 chips are available for about 1/4 of the price of the EasyDriver
board, so I was able to order some replacements. Despite being surface
mount chips they were relatively easy to replace, with a fine tipped
soldering iron. The hardest part being removing the old chips as the
solder wicks under the pins. Some brute force was required, but not too
much as it is easy to peel up the tracks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the stepper controllers proven to work (once refurbished) I ordered
an additional board to control the third axis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step was to get something in place to act as a controller. I
briefly considered writing my own but decided it would add a lot of work
and even more unknowns. After looking around online I decided on
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/grbl/grbl"&gt;GRBL&lt;/a&gt;. GRBL is a CNC controller
firmware designed to run on an Arduino, and thanks to a conveniently
timed workshop at Nottingham Hackspace I had an Arduino board I'd built
lying around. GRBL takes instructions in G-Code — which is a fairly
standard language for controlling CNC machines — and outputs step and
direction pulses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GRBL is designed to read G-Code through the Arduino's serial port, so a
USB to serial converter was required (and was also required to program
the Arduino). Fortunately, the trusty Minimus board came to the rescue,
along with some
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://rlab.org.uk/wiki/Projects/Minimus#USB_To_Serial_Project"&gt;instructions&lt;/a&gt;
provided by Reading Hackspace. With a Minimus acting as a USB to serial
adapter, I had the electronics side of the machine in place (albeit
cobbled together).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;quot;attachment_390&amp;quot; align=&amp;quot;alignnone&amp;quot; width=&amp;quot;1024&amp;quot;]&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moop.org.uk/index.php/2013/08/27/eshapeoko-part-1/2013-04-06-13-00-37/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Cobbled together CNC controller" class="size-full wp-image-390" src="http://www.moop.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/2013-04-06-13.00.37.jpg" style="width: 1024px; height: 613px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Cobbled together CNC controller[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll cover the mechanical side of it in another post.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry></feed>